<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd">
<book xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <bookinfo>
    <title>Spring Dynamic Modules for <trademark>OSGi</trademark> Service
    Platforms <superscript>*</superscript></title>
	
	<subtitle>Frequently Asked Questions</subtitle>
    <releaseinfo>&version;</releaseinfo>

    <authorgroup>
      <author>
        <firstname>Costin</firstname>
        <surname>Leau</surname>
      </author>
    </authorgroup>

    <legalnotice>
      <para><superscript>*</superscript> - OSGi is a trademark of <ulink url="http://www.osgi.org">
      the OSGi Alliance</ulink>,project name is pending OSGi Alliance approval.
      </para>
      
      <para>Copies of this document may be made for your own use and for
      distribution to others, provided that you do not charge any fee for such
      copies and further provided that each copy contains this Copyright
      Notice, whether distributed in print or electronically.</para>
    </legalnotice>
  </bookinfo>

  <toc />

  <chapter id="spring-osgi-faq">
    <title>Frequently Asked Questions</title>

    <section id="name-change">
      <title>What happened to "Spring OSGi" project name?</title>

        <para>The OSGi term is a trademark belonging to <ulink
        url="http://www.osgi.org/">The OSGi Alliance</ulink>. In order to
        comply with their guidelines, it was decided that the project name 
        be changed to "Spring Dynamic Modules for OSGi Service Platforms" 
        (aka Spring-DM). The new name is still pending final approval 
        by the OSGi Alliance. 
        The name change was the result of an amicable discussion between 
        the OSGi Alliance and Interface21. Interface21 is a member of the 
        OSGi Alliance, and the OSGi	Alliance remain very supportive of 
        the project.</para>
	</section>
	
	<section id="internal-package">
      <title>Why doesn't <literal>internal</literal> package have any
        javadocs?</title>

        <para>Package <literal>org.springframework.osgi.internal</literal> is
        meant (as the name implies) to be a private, non-public package. Thus,
        there is no documentation, support or compatibility guarantee for
        them. In fact, the Spring Dynamic Modules bundle does not even export
        them to prevent accidental usage. Some module bundles (such as 
        <literal>spring-osgi-core</literal>) do export some packages but these 
        are for internal usage within the rest of Spring-DM (such as
        <literal>spring-osgi-extender</literal>).</para>

        <para>If you find classes under this package, which you really, really
        depend on, then consider raising an issue on <ulink type=""
        url="http://opensource.atlassian.com/projects/spring/browse/OSGI">JIRA</ulink>
        to have access opened up.</para>
	</section>
	
	<section id="requirements">
	  <title>What are Spring Dynamic Modules requirements?</title>
	  <para>
	    Spring Dynamic Modules requires at least Java 1.4, OSGi 4.0 and Spring 2.5.
	    It might be possible to use Spring Dynamic Modules on a lower <ulink 
	    url="http://wiki.eclipse.org/index.php/Execution_Environments">execution environment</ulink>
	    (such <ulink url="http://java.sun.com/products/cdc/">CDC</ulink>) but 
	    it is not guaranteed to work.
	    Both Spring and Spring Dynamic Modules rely on <ulink url="http://java.sun.com/products/javabeans/">
	    JavaBeans</ulink> (java.beans package) which, unfortunately, is missing in most 
	    restricted environments. See this <ulink url="http://java.sun.com/products/cdc/reference/cdc_packages.pdf" 
	    type="application/pdf">PDF</ulink> for information on CDC profiles.
	    Note that, Spring 2.5 also requires Java 1.4.
	  </para>
	  <para>
	    Nevertheless, experiences and feedback on running Spring-DM in restricted environments 
	    is welcomed - please use our mailing list.
	  </para>
    </section>
    
    <section id="supported-osgi-platforms">
	  <title>What OSGi platforms are supported?</title>
	  <para>
	  Spring-DM requires an OSGi 4.0 platform. The framework has been tested
	  on <ulink url="http://www.eclipse.org/equinox/">Equinox</ulink>, <ulink url="http://felix.apache.org">Felix</ulink> 
	  and <ulink url="http://www.knopflerfish.org/">Knopflerfish</ulink> 
	  - in fact, the test suite is <ulink url="http://build.springframework.org:8085/bamboo/browse/OSGI">ran</ulink> 
	  against all of them as part of our continuous integration process.
	  </para>
	</section>
	
	<section id="osgi-intro">
	  <title>Where can I learn about OSGi?</title>
	  <para>
	   The best place to start is The Osgi Alliance <ulink url="http://www.osgi.org/">home</ulink> and 
	   <ulink url="http://www2.osgi.org/Main/HomePage">developer</ulink> pages which
	   provide the OSGi specifications, introductions and many links and blogs on the topic.
	   Below you can find a list (by no means comprehensive) of links to help you get started with OSGi: 
	  </para>
	  
	  <itemizedlist>
	   <listitem>Neil Bartlett's "Getting Started with OSGi" - <ulink url="http://neilbartlett.name/blog/osgi-articles/">here</ulink> and 
	   	<ulink url="http://www.eclipse.org/resources/?author=Neil%20Bartlett">here</ulink>.
	   </listitem>
	   <listitem>
   	    Equinox Documents - <ulink url="http://www.eclipse.org/equinox/documents/">here</ulink>
	   </listitem>
	  </itemizedlist>
	  
	  <para>
	   In addition, all OSGi implementation websites host detailed, step-by-step tutorials and introduction.
	  </para>
	  
	  <para>   
	   If you discover any additional materials useful for OSGi newbies, please let us know to update the list.
	   Thank you.
	  </para>
	</section>
	
	
	<section id="backport-util-concurrent">
	  <title>I get an exception about backport-util-concurrent library being required. Why is that?</title>

        <para>This exception is thrown only when running on Java 1.4 
        without backport-util-concurrent bundle installed.
        </para>
        <para>
        OSGi platform is a concurrent environment. Beans from different
        application contexts can interact with each other creating cycles 
        between their owning contexts. This means that the backing
        contexts have to be able to lookup and create/retrieve bean instances,
        all at the same time, on multiple threads. A traditional synchronised
        collection allows proper locking and thread coordination and prevents
        race conditions, but can cause very easily deadlocks.</para>

        <para>Consider two contexts each containing two beans: <mediaobject>
            <imageobject role="fo">
              <imagedata align="center"
                         fileref="src/docbkx/resources/images/deadlock.png"
                         format="PNG"/>
            </imageobject>

            <imageobject role="html">
              <imagedata align="center" fileref="images/deadlock.png"
                         format="PNG"/>
            </imageobject>

            <caption>
              <para>Inter-application context bean interaction</para>
            </caption>
          </mediaobject></para>

        <para>If both bean A and C are requested by two separate threads at
        the same time, this scenario will deadlock since each thread waits for
        the other one to release the "bean registry" lock even just for
        reading. However, when using a concurrent collection, reading doesn't
        require a lock so each thread can interact with the other context
        without waiting for a lock. Java 1.5 and upwards provide <ulink
        url="http://java.sun.com/j2se/1.5.0/docs/api/java/util/concurrent/package-summary.html">concurrent
        collections</ulink> under <literal>java.util</literal> package.
        However, since Java 1.4 does not, <ulink
        url="http://dcl.mathcs.emory.edu/util/backport-util-concurrent/">backport-util-concurrent</ulink>
        library is required.</para>
      </section>

	  <section id="maven-jdk6">
	    <title>I cannot build the sources when using JDK 6+. What can I do?</title>

        <para>The problem is caused by Maven <a href="http://maven.apache.org/guides/introduction/introduction-to-profiles.html">profiles</a> 
        feature which considers only a certain JDK version rather then all compatible versions. 
        As a workaround, one can build the sources, using JDK 5.0 (if annotations are needed) or 
        JDK 1.4.2 (without annotations or other JDK 5 specific features).
        </para>
      </section>
    
      <section id="logging">
        <title>How can I use logging in OSGi?</title>

        <para>OSGi platforms do not change the way libraries work, it just
        enforces tighter classloading. Thus, you can, in most of the cases,
        use the same logging strategy used in non-OSGi environments.</para>

        <para>Spring (and Spring-DM) use internally the <ulink
        url="http://commons.apache.org/logging/">commons-logging API</ulink>
        which acts as an "ultra-thin bridge between different logging
        implementations". In OSGi, just like in a non-OSGi environment, Spring
        and Spring-DM delegate all logging (including initialisation) to the
        actual commons-logging API implementation.</para>

        <para>Out of the box, <ulink type=""
        url="http://www.slf4j.org/">SLF4J</ulink> library is provided, which
        shares the same purpose as commons-logging but without the
        classloading discovery mechanism that causes loading issues, using
        static wiring (see the SLF4J site for more info). Please see <link linkend="commons-logging">this
        question</link > for more details on why commons-logging jar is not
        used.</para>

        <para>Spring-DM uses SLF4J on top of <ulink
        url="http://logging.apache.org/log4j/">Log4J</ulink> but this can be
        easily changed. As part of log4j initialisation, a
        <literal>log4j.properties</literal> or <literal>log4j.xml</literal>
        configuration fille needs to be present in the bundle classpath. This
        means that the configuration file has to be part of your bundle or one
        of its attached fragments. Besides SLF4J, for another OSGi-aware
        solution, one can try <ulink
        url="http://wiki.ops4j.org/dokuwiki/doku.php?id=pax:logging">Pax
        Logging</ulink>.</para>

        <para>To learn more about log4j setup process, follow this <ulink
        type=""
        url="http://logging.apache.org/log4j/1.2/manual.html">link</ulink>.</para>
      </section>

      <section id="commons-logging">
        <title>If you use commons-logging API, why rely on SLF4J and
        not the commons-logging jar?</title>

        <para>The commons-logging project provides the commons-logging API
        (<literal>commons-logging-api-nn.jar</literal>) along with an
        implementation (<literal>commons-logging-adapters-nn.jar</literal>)
        that provides a wrapper between the API and the actual logging libraries
        used underneath (such as log4j, java.util.logging, etc). However, in
        order to determine what implementation should be used, commons-logging
        library tries to do some classloading-based discovery that is fragile
        and can fail unexpectedly. In an strict classloading environment such
        as OSGi, this mechanism adds unnecessary complexity - that's why we
        decided to use SFL4J which is not just simpler and actively maintained
        but is also OSGi-friendly out of the box.</para>

        <para>For more information about commons-logging classloading
        problems, see these links: <ulink
        url="http://radio.weblogs.com/0122027/2003/08/15.html">#1</ulink>
        <ulink
        url="http://www.qos.ch/logging/thinkAgain.jsp">#2</ulink></para>
      </section>

      <section id="logging-impl-choice">
        <title>Why don't you use the OSGi logging service/[insert your favourite
        logging library in here]?</title>

        <para>It is completely up to you what logging implementation you want
        Spring-DM to use. To route log messages to the OSGi logging service, 
        just use a commons-logging API implementation that delegates to the 
        OSGi logging service, such as Pax Logging.</para>
      </section>
      
      
      <section id="osgi-wrapping">
        <title>I have to use [insert name] library/framework inside. What can I do?</title>
        
          <para>
          OSGi requires JARs to contain certain <literal>MANIFEST.MF</literal> entries which indicate what classes are 
          required and shared by each archive. This means that <emphasis>tradition</emphasis> jars cannot be used inside an OSGi environment. 
          To solve the problem one can:
          </para>
          <itemizedlist>
          	<listitem>
          	  <para>Use a repository of pre-wrapped libraries such as <ulink url="http://www.eclipse.org/orbit/">Orbit</ulink>,
          	  <ulink url="http://felix.apache.org/site/apache-felix-commons.html">Felix Commons</ulink> or Knopflerfish <ulink 
          	  url="http://www.knopflerfish.org/repo/index.html">repository</ulink>.
          	  Spring-DM also provides a small <ulink url="http://static.springframework.org/maven2-snapshots/org/springframework/osgi">
          	  repository</ulink> for its internal usage, which you might find helpful.</para> 
          	</listitem>
          	<listitem>
          	  <para>Wrap the necessary jars with proper OSGi manifest. While this can be done by hand, we strongly recommend Peter Kriens
          	  excellent <ulink url="http://www.aqute.biz/Code/Bnd">bnd</ulink> tool which can do this for you automatically.
          	  For Maven, see Felix <ulink url="http://felix.apache.org/site/maven-bundle-plugin-bnd.html">
          	  maven-bundle-plugin</ulink>.
          	  </para> 
          	</listitem>
          	<listitem>
          	  <para>Include the jar inside your OSGi bundle and include it in the bundle classpath through <emphasis>Bundle-ClassPath</emphasis>
          	  directive. See the OSGi specification for more information.</para>
          	</listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
	  </section>
	  
	  <section id="jdk-crippled-jta-api">
        <title><emphasis>java.lang.NoClassDefFoundError: javax/transaction/...</emphasis> when trying to do data access</title>
        
          <para>
          This problem is likely to be caused by bad class wiring. All 1.3+ JDKs include incomplete <emphasis>javax.transaction</emphasis> 
          and <emphasis>javax.transaction.xa</emphasis> packages for usage inside ORB environments. To address the problem, use a proper
          JTA library which contains all the classes from the forementioned packages and exports them with a specific version to prevent
          confusion.
          </para>
          <para>
          Spring-DM wraps JTA 1.1 library for OSGI environments which can be found at Spring snapshot repository. One can deploy this library
          and specify version 1.1 for <emphasis>javax.transaction*</emphasis> packages inside <emphasis>Import-Package</emphasis> header.
          By specifying the version, one can be sure that the proper package is used.
          </para>
          <para>
          Note that JTA 1.1 is compatible with version 1.0.1.
          </para>
	  </section>
      <!-- this should be part of an OSGi intro more likely -->

      <section id="auto-export-visibility">
        <title>The autoExport option doesn't work properly!</title>

        <para>autoExport flag, part of the service exporter, will discover and
        include for exporting only the <emphasis>visible</emphasis> interfaces/classes implemented
        by the service object. Consider class
        <literal>GenericApplicationContext</literal> which implements among
        others, interfaces <literal>BeanFactory</literal> (from
        <literal>org.springframework.beans.factory</literal> package) and
        <literal>ResourceLoader</literal>
        (<literal>org.springframework.core.io</literal>).</para>

        <para>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject role="fo">
              <imagedata align="center"
                         fileref="src/docbkx/resources/images/visibility.png"
                         format="PNG"/>
            </imageobject>

            <imageobject role="html">
              <imagedata align="center" fileref="images/visibility.png"
                         format="PNG"/>
            </imageobject>

            <caption>
              <para>Class Hierarchy</para>
            </caption>
          </mediaobject>
        </para>

        <para>Depending on your OSGi imports, the exporting bundle can see
        only one of the packages, none or both. Based on these visibility
        settings, the exporter will only export the classes that are 'known'
        to the exporting bundle. For example, if the exporting bundle sees
        <literal>org.springframework.core.io</literal> but not
        <literal>org.springframework.beans.factory</literal>, the service will
        be exported as a <literal>ResourceLoader</literal> but not as a
        <literal>BeanFactory</literal>. In fact, exporting the object as a
        <literal>BeanFactory</literal> will fail since the bundle doesn't see
        this interface and thus doesn't know how to handle its contract.</para>
      </section>
    </chapter>
</book>